Register of the American Committee on United Europe records
Hoover Institution Archives
American Committee on United Europe records
1949-1964
1951-1957
XX209
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes (3.3 linear feet)
Conference proceedings, newsletters, pamphlets, reports, clippings, and photographs relating to the European Federalists' Union, the European Movement, the European Youth Campaign, and affiliated organizations in promoting European political and economic unity.
American Committee on United Europe.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical note
The immediate post-World War II era witnessed a widespread dissemination of unitary ideology throughout Europe. Many countries had a proliferation of Europeanist and European Federalist movements, writings, initiatives, projects, and forming coalitions of groups geared towards a supranational institutional model for solidarity. In particular, the American Committee on United Europe (ACUE), founded in 1948, was an American organization sought to promote European integration to ensure promotion of the Marshall Plan and counter Communist influence.
ACUE was organized as a non-governmental agency by Allen Welsh Dulles, then head of a committee reviewing the organization of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) on behalf of the National Security Council (NSC), and William J. Donovan, former head of the wartime Office of Strategic Services (OSS). The ACUE worked closely with US government officials, particularly the Economic Cooperation Administration (ECA) and the National Committee for a Free Europe, which was being funded by the Henry Ford and John D. Rockefeller foundations. One of the aims of ACUE was to covertly finance the European Movement, Le Mouvement Européen (ME), an influential federalist organization in the post-war years. The European Movement brought together a network of people and organizations to mobilize advocacy a democratic, federal & enlarged union.
Concurrent to political mobilization towards unification special attention was given to the youth. For example, in 1948 the Union Fédéraliste Inter-Universitaire (UFI) was created as a group to disseminate federalist matters into universities. By 1949 ACUE began discussions with the leaders of ME to support initiatives aimed at introducing European integration to young people. The European Youth Campaign, Campagne Europeenne de la Jeunese, was created. The campaign was initially geared towards the French and German youth and last one year but grew into a long term educational initiative. was created as an arm of the European Movement and wholly funded and controlled by the US State Department and ACUE.
Around the same time period that formed the Union of European Federalists (UEF), a supranational organization established by the federalist movements present throughout the European Community. The Dutch and German movements become detached from the UEF and founded in 1956, the European federalist Action (AEF), while the UEF becomes, in 1959, the supranational MFE.
Scope and Content of Collection
The American Committee on United Europe (ACUE) records contain conference proceedings, newsletters, pamphlets, reports, clippings, and photographs relating to the European Movement, the European Federalists' Union, the European Youth Campaign and affiliated organizations in promoting European political and economic unity.
The collection is arranged according to its original order.
European Federalists' Union.; European Movement.; European Youth Campaign.; European federation.; United States--Foreign relations.; Youth movements--Europe.
- American Committee on United Europe (ACUE) File, 1949-1956
  Scope and Contents note
  Speeches, committee proceedings, poll reports, and the "Brussels Reports" relating to ACUE's adminstrative activities and interests in Europe.
  - The American Committee on United Europe, 1949-1956 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - World Peace Foundation conference proceedings and French politics reports, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 1:2)
- European Movement File, 1949-1959
  Speeches, conference proceedings, programs, reports, and printed matter related to European Movement activites and affilated organizations, arranged by chronological order.
  - European Parliamentary Union, 1949, 1954 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Economic Conference of the European Movement, 1949 April 20-29 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Action committee, circa 1950 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Pan Europa and printed matter, 1950, 1952-1954, 1960 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Conférence de Sociale de Rome, 1950 July 4-7
    - Pamphlets, 1950 July 4-7 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Preparation reports, 1950 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Speech by Paul-Henri Spaark at the meeting of the Council of Europe at Strasbourg, France, 1951 December 11 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - European League for Economic Co-Operation (ELEC), 1951, 1957 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - European Economic Conference in Westminister, England, 1954 January 29-February 1 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Programs, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Confédération européenne de l'agriculture (CEA), 1956, 1959 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - European Political Community Conference in Wiesbaden, Germany, 1959 January (Box-folder 2:7, Box-folder 3:1-2)
    General note
    Also titled "Kongress für die Europäische Politische Gemeinschaft/Conference pour la Communaute Politique Européenne."
  - American Committee on United Europe and coal and steel community information, printed matter, undated (Box-folder 3:3)
  - "La Fédération" and the French federalist movement, 1952, 1953, 1957 (Box-folder 3:4)
- European Youth Campaign File, 1951-1958
  Includes reports, newsletters, adminstrative records, speeches, and printed matter of the European Youth Campaign and association with ME.
  - Comission reports, circa 1951 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Drafts of Conference speeches, 1951 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Steering Committee and resolution proposals, Strasbourg, Germany, 1951 June 28 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Press mentions on campaigns, 1952, 1954, 1956 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Jeunesse d'Europe, 1952 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - "News of the European Youth Campaign," reports, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Reports, 1953 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - "World Peace Round Up," radio interview between Louis dailey and Luciano Sibille, 1953 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - European News Letter, review of the European Youth Campaign, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - "Voice of Europe," newsletters, 1953 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - European Youth Conference on Problems of Central and Eastern Europe, 1953 June 5-7 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - "European Youth Days,", 1953 October 9-10 (Box-folder 4:8)
    Includes reports, newsclippings, and photographs.
  - Maastricht report, 1954 July 20- August 1 (Box-folder 5:1)
    In collaboration with Des Jeunes du Mouvement des Federalistes Europeens and CEJ
  - Activity reports, 1954 November - 1955 August (Box-folder 5:2-4)
  - "Activités en France et Italie en faveur de la communauté européenne de défens,", 1954 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - European Youth Campaign newsletters, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Fact sheets, 1955 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Youth campaign training manual, 1955 July 10-20 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - "Commentary,", 1956-1958 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Pamphlets, circa 1950 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Booklets, circa 1950 (Box-folder 6:3)
- Union Européenne des Fédéralistes (UEF) File, 1949-1959
  Includes committee reports, conference proceedings, newsclippings, and ephemera related to UEF activites. Of particular note, by 1956, Dutch and German movements detached from the UEF and the European Federalist Action (AEF) was formed, while the UEF became, in 1959, the supranational MFE; some materials reflect the change in name and division.
  - Resolutions and reports, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 6:4)
    Note
    Includes the Schuman Plan and outlined organizational agreeance to the proposal.
  - Jeunesses Europeennes Federalistes (JEF), 1950-1951 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Central Committee reports and Fall Congress, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Administrative reports, 1951-1954 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Campaign memoranda, resolutions and appeals, 1951-1955 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Press mentions, 1952 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Federal Union, annual reports, and newsletters, 1949-1955 (Box-folder 7:3)
    The United Kingdom branch of the World Movement for World Federal Government and the UEF.
  - Centre International de Formation Européenne and UEF reports, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Centre d'Action Europeenne Federaliste (AEF), 1957-1959 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Congress of European People, treaty drafts, 1959 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Conference ephemera, 1959 (Box-folder 7:7)
- Union Fédéraliste Inter-Universitaire (UFI) File, 1949-1954
  Reports and conference printed matter relating to the orgnizational activities and philosophies.
  - Reports, motions, statues, 1949-1954 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - "Le Courier de L'Europe,", 1950 August 18-30 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Third Annual Congress at Saverne, France, 1951 September 7-12 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - International University, memorandum, 1953 (Box-folder 8:4)
  - J. Forment de Launay's "Fondation Europeenne de la Culture" dossier, 1959, 1964 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Human Rights Sub-Commission, undated (Box-folder 8:6)
- Mouvement Socialiste pour les états-Unis d'Europe (MSEUE) File, 1953-1958
  Reports, conference proceedings, and pamphlets.
  - "Sixième Congrès du M.S.E.U," in Liège, 1953 May (Box-folder 8:7)
  - "Nouvelles du M.S.,", 1954 (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Mouvement Gauche, circa 1950 (Box-folder 8:9)
  - Notes for "common steps" report, 1955 October (Box-folder 8:10)
  - Pamphlets, 1956 (Box-folder 8:11)
  - "Seminar über die Politische Einigung Europas,", 1958 January (Box-folder 8:12)